Hey, remember back in unit two when we
talked about the First Great Awakening?
Well, apparently many Americans went
ahead and fell back asleep with
reference to their souls and that means
it's time to wake their crap all the way
up yet again. That's right, it's time
for the Second Great Awakening. So, if
you're ready to get them brain cows
milked, let's get to it. Okay, now
remember a few videos ago when we talked
about the Market Revolution and the
expansion of voting rights which
fundamentally changed the US economy and
society and politics. And by the way,
the only acceptable answer to that
question is a hearty heck yes cuz I'm
not going to cover it again. Well, those
developments also created the conditions
for a massive religious revival in the
first half of the 19th century known as
the Second Great Awakening. And I don't
know about you, but that just makes me
want to cinch up my comparison pants and
see how that relates to the First Great
Awakening. And because I'm feeling
sassy, let's start with the
similarities. So, both Great Awakenings
were mass religious movements that
spread throughout much of the American
territory. And as such, they both
provided Americans with a common
experience and religious vocabulary that
served to unite people from different
regions. Additionally, both movements
spawned new Christian denominations
while also spurring the growth of
existing denominations and I'll say a
little bit more about that later. But
now, let's consider the differences. So,
preachers in the First Great Awakening
were overwhelmingly Calvinist and
emphasized individual sin and individual
conversion. In fact, according to
preachers like Jonathan Edwards, each
individual person was born in sin and
therefore was so wretched and sinful
that their hearts are evil and black all
the way to the bottom. And so, without a
powerful religious conversion to the way
of Christ, the human being is in no way
capable of making a choice that
qualifies as good or right. You know,
I'm not a Christian, but even so, I
think I'll have an Egg McMuffin sandwich
for lunch. Apart from Christ's
intervention, your sandwich besmirches
the glory of God, you black-hearted
turd. Anyway, all that meant for the
most part that the First Great Awakening
had precious little to say about making
society a better place to live. I mean,
if only a few elect Christians were ever
going to make it to heaven anyway, you
might as well just let the
glory-besmirching sandwich-munchers go
down in flames. But in the Second Great
Awakening, which lasted roughly 50 years
from 1790 to 1840, preachers emphasized
more of the innate goodness of human
beings and their capacity to choose to
live holy lives. And that meant that
this movement focused far more on
societal reformation as the outflow of
religious conversion. difference here is
that preachers in this awakening
believed and preached that Christians,
by their efforts of social reform, could
actually bring the perfection of the
kingdom of God to earth. And so, this
religious movement, not surprisingly,
spurred an endless number of groups and
voluntary organizations that tried to
make American society a better place to
live and rid the land of its communal
sin. Okay, now before I get into the
causes of this religious revival, it may
be that your APUSH grade needs a little
reviving of its own. And for that, let
me introduce you to my APUSH Heimler
Review Guide. It has everything you need
to study as fast as possible so you can
get an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May. It's got exclusive
whole unit [music] review videos that
you're not going to see here on YouTube,
note guides to follow along, practice
multiple-choice questions for each unit,
full-length practice exams, and answer
keys for every dang bit of it. So, if
that's the kind of help you need, then
get that clicky finger out and check
that link in the description. Okay, so
let's consider the causes of the Second
Great Awakening and there are no less
than three of them. First, you have the
expansion of democracy. So, during this
period, more and more Americans believed
that they were entitled to participate
in the franchise and therefore worked to
expand the right to vote from a small
elite group of propertied white men to
an acceptance of universal white male
suffrage. So says you, how does more
democracy lead to more spirituality? A
fine question says I and here's the
connection. You see, the Calvinism of
the First Great Awakening emphasized the
doctrine of predestination which taught
that God had decided before the creation
of the world which people would be saved
and which would be damned. And the
saved, known as the elect, were much
smaller in number than the mass of
humanity that would be damned. And if
that smells a little elitist to you,
then your sniffer is working just fine.
But in the Second Great Awakening, the
doctrine of predestination was almost
entirely abandoned and instead,
preachers emphasized the innate goodness
of human beings and the possibility of
every person to achieve salvation by
believing in the gospel and adopting a
life of Christian morality. In other
words, salvation was now open to all,
which was a very democratic notion. And
you can see this principle, for example,
in the way these revivals took place and
who was included. So, on the frontier
and in rural areas, revivals were
organized into camp meetings. These were
all-day gatherings in fields where
multiple preachers filled the day with
emotionally charged sermons interlaced
with congregational singing and praying.
And as a general rule, many of these
preachers had no formal education, which
was a big departure from the luminaries
of the First Great Awakening like
Jonathan Edwards and George Whitefield.
Additionally, the crowds that attended
the camp meetings were unusually
diverse, including whites and blacks,
both enslaved and free, as well as
women. In fact, in some cases, black
preachers and women preachers held the
stage and gathered their own following.
As a result, Christian denominations
that allowed for such diversity grew
rapidly, especially the Baptist and the
Methodist. And the Methodist grew
especially fast because their preachers
were circuit riders, which meant that
they traveled throughout a region
preaching and seeking converts. And one
particularly famous frontier preacher
was the Methodist Peter Cartwright whose
circuit range from Tennessee to
Illinois. And he traveled that circuit
on horseback for decades and by the end
of his life, he had traveled, by some
estimates, around 300,000 miles trying
to light the fire of Christian
conversion. And growing up on the
frontier, he had no formal education and
thus represents the Second Great
Awakening's democratization of faith.
Okay, the second cause of the new
religious revival was the rise of
individualistic beliefs. So, intimately
intertwined with the expansion of
democracy was the growing belief in the
triumph of the individual as the most
basic unit of society. And this idea was
encouraged through the Transcendentalist
movement, which we'll talk a lot more
about in the next video. Anyway, one of
their main emphases was that a person
needed to find his or her own way in the
world without submitting to the rules,
regulations, and mores of the wider
society. And so, Second Great Awakening
preachers used the language of
individualism to challenge their hearers
to have a personalized religious
conversion and direct the power of that
conversion toward the reformation of
society. And then, the third cause of
the Second Great Awakening was a
reaction against rationalism. Now,
during the era of independence and the
creation of a new government, religious
beliefs were kind of sidelined for the
triumph of rationalistic beliefs,
especially those promoted by
Enlightenment thought. For example,
Thomas Paine in his book The Age of
Reason argued that religious belief and
churches were instruments of control and
conformity that suffocated people's
access to liberty. And so, many of the
founders channeled their religious
instincts into a more rationalistic and
less emotional form of belief known as
deism. It was a belief that God was
something like a cosmic clockmaker who
made the world and everything therein as
a clock, then wound it up with the laws
of physics, and then let it tick away
with no further intervention on his
part. Therefore, deists rejected any
reports of miracles in the Bible since
that would imply that God remained
active in the world after the moment of
creation. The point is, deism was a
belief system that allowed for
intellectual ascent without any of the
emotionalism of prior iterations of the
Christian faith. But as the Second Great
Awakening began, its preachers rejected
that dry intellectualism in favor of
highly charged emotional appeals, which
was influenced by the same romanticism
that produced the highly emotional art
forms of the period. Anyway, if
preachers like Peter Cartwright lit the
fire of revival in rural and frontier
areas, Charles Grandison Finney revived
the crap out of America's urban
population. And he focused much of his
effort in Rochester, New York City, and
his soaring oratory held crowds
spellbound. He made use of highly
charged emotional appeals and spoke in
plain language filled with metaphors and
allusions that common people could
understand. And furthermore, Finney's
preaching thundered with appeals for
Christians to reform society, especially
drunkenness and slavery, because in
doing so, they were ushering in the
perfect kingdom of God. Now, the
emotionalism of Finney and preachers
like him reached its height in what
became known as the Burned-Over District
of Western New York. It was called this
because the preachers had converted so
many people with their hellfire and
brimstone messages that it appeared that
there was no one left to convert. And
ultimately, this religious movement
would set up the entire apparatus for
widespread social reform in the next few
decades and I'll talk all about that in
the next video. Okay, you can click here
to watch my other videos for unit four
or you can click here to grab my APUSH
Heimler Review Guide, which is going to
help you get an A in your class and a
five on your exam in May. I'm really
glad you came around and I'll catch on
the flip-flop. Heimler out.